Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at boosting our GLP-1
the way mother nature intended.
Plant-predominant diets may play
a "major role in reversing
the obesity
and chronic disease epidemics,"
just as plant-based
dietary interventions
may arrest or even reverse
type 2 diabetes
and cardiovascular disease
on an individual basis.
In a previous video,
I showed how a tofu burger
boosted levels
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
higher than a meat burger
in both people with diabetes
and without,
even though the two burgers
were matched
for calories
and macronutrients.
One thing may have given
the plant-based meal an edge,
though, at least over time:
increased fiber.
The bacterial fermentation
of dietary fibers in the colon
produces short-chain fatty acids
called acetate, propionate,
and butyrate, which, in turn,
stimulate release of GLP-1.
In this way, prebiotics,
like dietary fiber,
represent
an alternative strategy
for boosting production
of GLP-1.
In contrast, a bacterial
breakdown product of tryptophan,
which is concentrated
in animal protein,
has been found
to have opposite effects
on GLP-1 release.
How do we know fiber-derived
short-chain fatty acids
boost GLP-1 in the first place?
Well, all three circulating
short-chain fatty acids
were associated with
higher GLP-1 concentrations
in the blood,
but that doesn’t prove
cause-and-effect.
For that, you need to stick
tubes in people’s butts.
Getting a rectal infusion
of acetate
indeed causes GLP-1 levels
to go up.
And the amount of acetate
concentrations in the blood
reached after rectal infusion
were within an achievable range,
in the ballpark
of what you’d get
eating 15 or more grams
of fiber a day,
here in the form
of oat bran cereal and muffins.
There’s a third way
to get appetite-suppressing
short-chain fatty acids
in our bloodstream
besides the top-down approach
of eating healthy food
and the bottoms-up approach
of getting them squirted
in your tush.
When you consume vinegar,
its acetic acid is rapidly
neutralized into acetate.
No wonder vinegar
has evidently been used
to treat obesity for centuries.
Does this all translate
into reducing cravings,
eating less,
and losing weight?
Let’s scan people’s brains
and find out.
Researchers delivered
propionate,
a fiber-derived,
short-chain fatty acid,
into the colons
of study participants
while showing them images of
pizza, cakes, and chocolates,
and found that increasing
colonic propionate
seemed to reduce
brain activation
in the reward centers
of the brain.
This was accompanied by
a decrease in subjective appeal
of these kinds of foods,
they didn’t look as tasty,
and this translated
into reduced caloric intake
at a buffet meal.
Note that this effect
didn’t seem to correlate
with GLP-1 changes, though;
so, it’s possible
that short-chain fatty acids
produced in the colon
are accessing the brain directly
and reducing appetite
some other way.
Regardless,
does the boost in GLP-1
and the short-term reduction
of caloric intake
from the direct delivery
of propionate to the colon
translate into
better weight control
in overweight adults?
Yes, long-term colonic
propionate delivery
prevents body weight gain,
particularly deep abdominal fat,
and may even reduce liver fat
in those with
fatty liver disease.
So, you’d expect prebiotic
trials to show the same,
and sometimes they worked,
boosting GLP-1
and driving down hunger,
but overall, human interventions
with prebiotics
have shown mixed results.
And that’s putting it lightly.
Effects on GLP-1 appear
to be highly contradictory,
with different isolated dietary
fibers bumping GLP-1 up,
some dropping it down,
and others having no effect.
In some cases, it’s possible
that macronutrients
that would otherwise
stimulate GLP-1
might get caught up
in viscous, fibrous masses
and result in lower levels.
Regardless, results for
short-term prebiotic trials
are said to be
"completely inconclusive"
for GLP-1.
One problem may be the dose.
For example, in this study,
researchers tested
refined-grain bread
versus whole-grain bread,
and although the whole-grain
bread improved satiety,
it had no effect on GLP-1.
The difference in fiber content
was only about five grams,
though, which may not be enough.
In this study,
study participants
were randomized
to get either 5 or 10 grams
of a fiber supplement
called Fibersol,
and the five-gram dose appeared
to have no greater effect
on GLP-1 than placebo.
Only the 10-gram dose worked,
which is about two tablespoons.
Similarly, there were
significant delays in hunger
and increased satiety
after 10 grams, but not five.
And studies like this
may only last a few hours.
The more fiber-rich foods
you eat,
the more you foster the growth
of more fiber-feeders,
which means even more
GLP-1 secretion over time.
Eating more fiber-rich foods
may eventually even promote
the emergence of more
GLP-1 secreting cells
in our intestinal lining.
Check out this study.
Adaptation
of colonic fermentation
and GLP-1 secretion with
increased wheat fiber intake
for not a few hours
but an entire year.
People who eat whole grains
tend to get less diabetes,
but even if you switch to
whole wheat for weeks or months,
there doesn’t seem
to be much improvement
in blood sugar control.
It turns out
it may take longer than that
for our colon to adapt
to the increased fiber intake.
Colonic adaptation
to increased wheat fiber intake
takes many months
but eventually results
in increased
short fatty acid production
and GLP-1 secretion.
This was found
when people were randomized
to a year of either All Bran
or Rice Krispies cereal
for breakfast.
And there was
a significant increase
in short-chain
fatty acid production
and GLP-1 secretion
in the higher-fiber group,
but it took 9 to 12 months
for these benefits to develop.
And finally,
people may not understand
the complexity of dietary fiber,
thinking that
it’s a single nutrient,
but there are literally
thousands of types of fiber
in plant foods,
and each one may support
different communities
of bacteria in our gut.
That’s the reasoning
behind recommendations
that people take
a "50-food challenge,"
eating at least 50
different plant foods a week
to achieve a diet
diverse enough
to feed a vast spectrum
of bacteria.
Those who get more fiber
in their diet
are significantly less likely
to get heart disease,
and die from heart disease.
Less likely to get
cardiovascular disease
in general, and less likely
to die from it.
Less likely to have a stroke,
less likely to get diabetes
and colorectal cancer,
less likely to die
from cancer across the board,
and less likely to die
from all causes put together.
But all of this
is for fiber from food.
In terms of fiber intake
for optimal health,
the first line of defense
for disease prevention
is to focus on fiber from foods
rather than supplements.
For the treatment of disease,
there is a lack
of evidence-based research
to support the use
of most isolated fiber types.
Take that supplement Fibersol,
for example.
Fibersol is
a registered trademark
of the Matsutani
Chemical Industry Company,
the one who invented it.
"Looking to increase
the fiber content
of a finished product?
Check out
our innovation success stories."
Eat your donut cookie
whipped cream milkshake,
it’s got fiber!
Maybe better to stick to foods
that were invented instead
by Mother Nature.
The majority of cells
producing GLP-1
are located
at the end of the gut,
in our large intestine.
But prebiotics
don’t represent the only
"slow digestion-oriented
dietary strategy"
to sustain
the secretion of GLP-1.
Prebiotics can be used
to promote metabolic health
and longevity by stimulating
intestinal production of GLP-1,
and so too
can the drug Acarbose,
which acts as a starch blocker,
inhibiting the enzymes
that would normally digest
carbohydrates earlier
in the small intestine.
Acarbose-induced transfer
of carbs to the lower parts
of the intestine
increases GLP-1 levels.
And since changes in GLP-1
correlate with weight loss
in those on the drug,
it’s reasonable to suspect
that GLP-1 is a mediator
of the favorable impact
of acarbose therapy
on weight control.
There’s also a third strategy,
eating "lente" carbohydrates,
from the Latin lentus for slow.
Instead of taking a drug to slow
dietary carbohydrate digestion,
what about just choosing a diet
centered around slow-digesting
"lente" carbohydrates
to achieve comparable benefits?
That’s the theory, anyway.
So, that means pasta,
beans, groats,
meaning structurally intact
grain kernels,
as well as sprouted grains.
Let’s start with beans.
Here, researchers found
enhanced secretion
of satiety-promoting
gut hormones
after the consumption
of white bread
that had been enriched with
coarsely ground chickpea flour,
and the more chickpea
it contained,
the higher
the GLP-1 levels spiked,
but where are you going
to find chickpea bread?
What about just eating beans?
Asking people to eat five cups
(850-900 g) of beans a week
spontaneously led
to health benefits
similar to those seen
after asking people
to cut 500 calories
out of their daily diet,
but there was no change
in GLP-1 levels.
What about cocoa beans?
I wish, but sadly,
no effect of dark chocolate
on GLP-1 either.
The one pasta study I could find
also failed to bump GLP-1,
but the one
sprouted grain study I found
showed higher GLP-1 response
to sprouted bread,
compared to four other types
of bread,
which didn’t differ
significantly from each other.
Eleven- or 12-grain bread
was no different
than white bread?
That’s what’s generally found
when comparing products
made with whole-grain flour
to refined-grain flour;
there aren’t any immediate
right-after-the-meal effects
of whole wheat bread compared
to white bread, for example.
You can’t just eat bread
and expect some kind
of "doughzempic" effect,
because, as I explained
in my last few videos,
food structure is critical
for optimal health.
When grains are milled
into flour,
whether whole wheat or white,
their cell walls are ruptured
and the starch spills out
and never makes it
down to our colon;
so, we don’t get
their added benefit.
This is one of the reasons
former Harvard nutrition chair
Walt Willett
has argued that the term
whole grain
should probably be reserved for
only whole intact grain kernels,
otherwise known as groats,
the "wholiest" of grains.
In my book How Not to Diet,
I talk about my BROL bowl,
a prebiotic mix
that includes barley groats,
rye groats, and oat groats.
What effect might they have
on GLP-1?
If you give people bread
containing some
whole intact barley groats,
there’s no immediate difference
in GLP-1 levels
in the subsequent three hours,
but the groats
wouldn’t even have had time
to make it down to your colon
that quickly.
However,
after your good bacteria
have had a chance
to break open their cell walls,
you get a greater,
higher GLP-1 bump
more than 12 hours later,
at breakfast the next day.
The question, though,
is whether that translates
into a suppressed appetite.
And indeed, lower food intake
not just at breakfast,
but also at lunch the next day,
14 hours later!
Having barley kernels
at an evening meal
not only increased GLP-1
the next day,
boosting blood levels
by 43 percent at breakfast,
but feelings of hunger
decreased
during the entire next day,
and the research participants
ate about 100 fewer calories
of an all-you-can-eat lunch,
just because they had
some barley groats
fourteen hours before.
Eat barley groats
three days in row
and on the fourth day
see a 56 percent increase
in the level of GLP-1
in your blood.
What about rye groats?
Eat rye groats for supper,
and more than 10 hours later,
your GLP-1 levels are up,
and your appetite is down.
Researchers found
that participants
had an increased
subjective feeling of satiety
during the course
of the entire next day.
So, rye groats
"demonstrate anti-diabetes
and anti-obesity potential
as manifested by
enhanced blood sugar control
and increased GLP-1
and the accompanying
appetite suppression."
And there was a correlation
between the short-chain
fatty acids,
acetate and propionate,
and GLP-1 response,
suggesting that, indeed,
we may have
our good gut bugs to thank
for the beneficial effects.
The cells that produce
the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
in response to calorie exposure
are concentrated
all the way down
at the end
of our digestive tract,
which is why our appetites
are not suppressed very much
these days.
The majority
of the calories we eat
are absorbed early
in our digestive tract;
so, they never make it down
far enough.
When we eat a donut,
its fat, sugar, and starch
get absorbed quickly, high up,
before reaching the part
of our digestive tract
where we produce
most of the hormone
that suppresses our appetite.
So, from a GLP-1 standpoint,
it’s like we never ate
much of anything.
No wonder we reach for donut #2.
How can we eat a donut
and still get GLP-1 activation?
Surgery!
Bariatric surgery
can involve cutting out
part of our small intestine
so some of the donut calories
may reach the end of it
after all.
What if you want to eat a donut,
still get GLP-1 activation,
and keep your anatomy intact?
Drugs!
By injecting GLP-1
mimicking drugs, like Ozempic,
you can get GLP-1 activation
no matter what you eat.
You could also take
the starch-blocker drug acarbose
to slow the digestion
of carbohydrates,
or the fat-blocker drug orlistat
to slow the digestion of fats.
But what if you want
GLP-1 activation
without drugs or surgery?
Well, you could try
not eating donuts.
Ancestral humans
might have consumed
as much as 100 grams
of fiber daily.
That’s about six times
what most of us are getting
these days.
We evolved eating massive
amounts of whole plant foods,
the only place
fiber is found in abundance.
So, by eating
the way nature intended,
we can release GLP-1
which helps explain why
a whole food, plant-based diet
is one of the most powerful
weight loss interventions
ever published.
But what do we do
about our cravings?
What are some
therapeutic approaches
to addressing them?
Well, there are drugs,
of course,
but in terms
of food-based interventions,
there are thylakoids,
which are just the
chlorophyll-rich membranes
inside leaves where
photosynthesis takes place.
Thylakoids act as fat blockers,
delaying our digestion of fats
and promoting the release
of satiety hormones like GLP-1.
When we eat thylakoids,
in other words, when we bite
into a leaf of spinach,
for instance,
the thylakoid membranes
are able to resist
our digestive enzymes.
They can last for hours
in our gut
before finally
being broken down,
and it is in those hours
when they work their magic.
Thylakoids glom
onto tiny droplets of fat
in our digestive tract,
and, in this way,
powerfully slow our digestion
of fat.
And that means more GLP-1.
Yes, GLP-1 is a hormone
that is being developed
as an anti-obesity drug
(this was published two years
before Ozempic).
But thylakoids
can cause our natural,
endogenous release of GLP-1,
which is an easier
and more physiological way
to enhance GLP-1 levels
to achieve satiety
and calorie balance.
But does it
actually cut cravings?
Spinach extracts
were disguised in jam and juice
to sneak thylakoids
undetected into meals,
and those unwittingly eating
the equivalent
of about half a cup (100 g)
of cooked spinach
felt significantly less hungry
and more satiated
over the next few hours.
Give someone the equivalent
of a shot of wheatgrass juice
or what they might get
in a "green drink"
or green smoothie,
and not only do they feel
more satiated,
but their cravings for sweet,
salty, and fatty snacks,
such as potato chips,
chocolate, and cinnamon buns,
drop by about a third.
Feed them candy anyway,
and those who unknowingly
had been snuck some spinach,
report liking the sweets
significantly less.
The satiating power of greens
has been attributed
to their high fiber
and water contents
and low calorie density,
but the thylakoids
may be their secret weapon,
presumably because of
the increased release of GLP-1
following
thylakoid supplementation.
In a systematic review
of randomized controlled trials
on the effects
of thylakoid intake
on appetite and weight loss,
hunger-suppressing effects
of thylakoids
were reported in all studies
that directly measured
hunger and fullness.
But what about the weight loss?
Would the GLP-induced reduction
of cravings and hunger
from greens
translate into losing pounds?
I showed how starting your day
with a single dose of thylakoids
increased
feelings of satiety
and decreased hunger and
cravings for snacks and sweets
throughout the day.
We’re talking about
a powdered spinach extract
equivalent to just half a cup
(80 g) of cooked greens.
Significantly less desire
for salty snacks
over the next nine hours
compared to placebo,
with just one dose of greens.
Significantly less desire
for sweet snacks, sweet and fat,
snacks in general.
Thylakoids, thus,
provide a powerful strategy
to suppress the urge
for so-called "palatable" food,
potato chips, chocolate,
cinnamon buns, and the like.
But despite the lower hunger
and greater satiety,
food intake throughout the day
was not significantly affected.
In a systematic review
of randomized clinical trials
on the effects
of thylakoid intake
on appetite and weight loss,
the hunger-suppressing effects
of thylakoids
were reported
in all the relevant studies,
but what about
the weight-loss part?
Instead of a single dose
of greens,
what about the same dose
every day for three months?
The title gives it away:
you get a loss of body weight,
reduced cravings,
and increased release
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1.
The average amount
of weight loss
was only about three pounds
(1 kg),
but the study participants
also got
a significant drop
in cholesterol of 20 points,
the drop in cholesterol preceded
significant weight loss;
so, the cholesterol benefit
wasn’t just because
weight was being lost.
And 20 points?
That’s the kind
of result you get
using an earlier class
of cholesterol-lowering drugs.
GLP-1 was also boosted by about
40 percent, and check this out:
significantly lower
cravings for sweets
even 11 hours
after spinach intake.
And, remember,
the spinach powder was hidden;
so, people didn’t know
which group they were in,
didn’t know if they were getting
greens or placebo.
And 11 hours later,
they were, like, chocolate?
Eh, no thanks.
Uh, got any spinach?
So, not only were there
decreased cravings
in the six hours
prior to lunch,
but also decreased cravings
afterwards--
all from just getting
that one single dose of greens
in the morning.
That’s the power of GLP-1.
Now, one of the authors
had a conflict of interest,
affiliations with companies
trying to commercialize
thylakoid products,
and you can see it in the spin.
They described
the spinach extract
as markedly
reducing body weight,
but I wouldn’t consider
three pounds (1 kg) "markedly."
They boast that
the 6 percent weight loss
was comparable to an older GLP-1
drug available at the time,
suggesting that increasing
the natural release of GLP-1
may be as efficient
as pharmacological agents
for the treatment for obesity.
Of course, our new GLP-1 drugs
can decrease body weight
by more than 6 percent,
but the 6 percent loss
in this study
was from baseline,
not compared to placebo.
Those on the placebo lost about
4 percent of their body weight;
so, weight loss
attributable to the spinach
was more like only 2 percent.
And another eight-week study
found no significant difference
at all.
So, when they took
their supplement
to the European equivalent
of the U.S. Food and Drug
Administration
to try to make
a weight-loss health claim,
the panel was, like,
a 1 percent weight loss?
That’s really not going
to do much.
Whether these appetite-lowering
effects of thylakoids
could be a useful strategy
in controlling obesity
in the long term
is still ambiguous.
More studies are needed.
And, here we go, the latest
thylakoid weight loss study.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
with that same dose
equivalent to half a cup (80 g)
of cooked greens,
and there was a significant
decrease in body weight,
fat mass, waist circumference,
waist-to-height ratio,
and body mass index (BMI)
compared to placebo--
and, by a decent amount.
Individuals in the spinach group
lost 15 pounds (7 kg),
compared to 7
in the placebo group.
Eight more pounds (3 kg)
of weight loss on greens
than placebo.
And that included
8 pounds of straight fat,
including 4 more centimeters
off the waist.
So, based on a systematic review
of the potential effects
of thylakoids
in the management of obesity,
eating green can suppress
hunger, reduce food intake,
and result in weight loss.
Greens can offer a means
to strengthen our resolve
to refrain from eating,
especially when we’re in a kind
of high-doughnut environment
where there is
"superfluous access
to foods processed
to deliver qualities
that some may find
irresistible."
It’s interesting,
even supplementing a breakfast
that was only 11 percent fat
with thylakoids resulted in
decreased hunger and cravings,
suggesting that there
might be other mechanisms
for the appetite-suppressive
effect of thylakoids
beyond just slowing
the digestion of fat.
What’s the best way to get them?
Not from the supplement aisle,
but rather the produce aisle.
And remember, that’s where
the chlorophyll is found;
so, you can see
with your own eyes
which veggies
have more thylakoids
by how dark green they are.
What happens
when you cook greens?
Blanched for 15 seconds or so
in steaming or boiling water,
they actually get
even brighter green,
but if you cook them too long,
they eventually turn
a drab olive brown.
When greens are overcooked,
their thylakoids
physically degrade,
along with their ability
to slow fat absorption.
Within that first minute
of cooking,
when the green gets
even more vibrant, though,
there’s a slight boost
in fat-blocking ability.
So, you can gauge
thylakoid activity
in both the grocery store
and in your kitchen
with your own two eyes.
We have been chewing on leaves
for millions of years,
but today,
the greenest thing
about some people’s diets
may be a St. Patty’s Day pint.
Americans have averaged fewer
than two grams of spinach a day,
not even half a teaspoon.
But our bodies were designed
to have thylakoids
passing through our systems
on a daily basis;
so, that delay in fat absorption
we get from them
can be thought of
as our default, normal state.
It’s only when we eat diets
deficient in greens
that we suffer
the accelerated fat digestion
that undercuts
our natural satiety mechanisms.
In the journal of the Society
of Chemical Industry,
a group of food technologists
argued that,
given their
fat-blocking benefits,
"thylakoid membranes
could be incorporated
in functional foods
as a new promising
appetite-reducing ingredient,"
or you can just get them
the way Mother Nature intended.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.